One day in physics class, you’re learning
about gravity, and your friend tells you that
they exert a stronger gravitational force
on you than the nearest star beyond our sun,
proxima centauri.
You have a mass of sixty kilograms, as does
your friend, who is sitting two meters away.
Proxima centauri has a mass of 2.45 times
ten to the twenty-nine kilograms, and it is
4.01 times ten to the sixteen meters away.
So is your friend correct?
Which exerts more gravity on you, your friend,
or the star?
To answer this, we will need to use Newton’s
law of universal gravitation, so if you missed
that tutorial, check it out right now.
If you know what to do, give this calculation
a try.
This is easy to solve if we know this equation.
All we do is plug in the masses and distances
involved, as well as the gravitational constant.
First, for your friend, we plug in sixty and
sixty as the masses, and two meters as the
distance between you.
We square that and evaluate, and we should
get six times ten to the negative eight Newtons.
This is an extremely tiny force, which explains
why people don’t slowly drift towards each
other when sitting in a room.
Now let’s do one for the star.
We replace the mass of your friend with the
mass of the star, but we also change this
value to the distance to the star, so we have
a huge number on top, but we have a pretty
big number on the bottom, too, and we have
to square it, so when we evaluate this, we
get 6.1 times ten to the negative thirteen
Newtons.
As small as the first number was, this one
is a hundred thousand times smaller, so it
looks like your friend was right, none of
the stars in the universe apart from the sun
can have any significant gravitational influence
on the earth.
Take that, astrology!